Finding Aid for Norman Olson Papers, 1950-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Norman Olson Papers 1950-2001
Olson, Norman.
2010208 Aa 2
One of the original organizers of the Michigan Militia, and founder of the Northern Michigan Regional Militia, organizations established to protect second amendment rights and individual liberties from government authority. Personal records, resource material and publications related to the activities of Norman Olson and the Michigan Militia.
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Amy Cooter, a militia researcher, in October 2010. Donor no. 10428.
No addition to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research. However, access to the collection requires the researcher to sign an access agreement preserving confidentiality of names recorded in certain files.
Norman Olson was a gun shop owner and pastor from Alanson, Michigan. He and one other person, Ray Southwell, founded the Michigan Militia in 1994. They created this organization in reaction to what they perceived as the government overstepping its authority during the 1990's, in the process threatening personal rights, especially on issues relating to the ownership of firearms and property rights. They expressed additional concern over the United Nations and a concept of an emerging "New World Order". The Michigan Militia faced intense scrutiny from media and law enforcement following the Oklahoma City Bombing. Two bomb suspects, Timothy McVeigh and Terry Nichols, were said to have attended a meeting of the organization but were not actually members. The group's leadership forced Olson to resign as commander in a matter of weeks after the bombing because of his view that linked the Japanese to the Oklahoma City attack. In July 1995 Olson broke from the Michigan Militia entirely, after having lost an internal election to regain his position as commander. He went on to form his own militia, the Northern Michigan Regional Militia.
This second organization shared much of the same ideas and ideology as the first. Olson strongly believed that the federal government and United Nations were a very real threat to the individual rights of American citizens. Within the context of US and world history, and militaristic organization, the Michigan Militia and Northern Michigan Regional Militia sought to recruit, educate, and train members to defend themselves and others against any such encroachment by government authority.
The Papers of Norman Olson are arranged into two series: Personal Records, and Collected Resources and Publications. The collection documents aspects of his personal life and interests during his time as a leader and member of the Michigan Militia, as well as his understanding of politics, government, and American society.
Subjects:
Firearms ownership--United States.; Government, Resistance to--United States.; Michigan Militia Corps.; Militia movements--Michigan.; Northern Michigan Regional Militia.; Olson, Norman.; Right-wing extremists--Michigan.
- Personal Records 1993-2001
  The Personal Records series (2 linear feet) is comprised primarily of correspondence, faxes, as well as other documents. Olson kept these as a record of internal exchange within the organized militia network, and of communication with other organizations, public officials or agencies, and individual persons. Documents retained by Olson also relate to gun purchases, legal proceedings, and other events of significance.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence with individual persons 1994-2001, undated, 11 folders (Box 1)
      (confidentiality protected; researcher must sign access agreement)
    - Correspondence with organizations 1994-1998, 2001, undated, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with government officials and other federal agencies 1993-1999, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and faxes from internal network of Michigan Militias 1994-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and records from other militia 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence not written by, or addressed to, Norman Olson 1994-1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Other materials received through the mail (Box 2)
    - Faxes, other 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Legal Cases
    - Bois Blanc Township vs. Michael and Christine Stitt 1996-1999 (Box 2)
    - Franklin C. Smith vs. Stanton Kaplan 1999 (Box 2)
    - James P. Dacey vs. Town of Perry 1996 (Box 2)
    - Joe Hoyal vs. George H. Connell Jr. 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Ray Southwell vs. Southern Poverty Law Center 1996 (Box 2)
    - State of Oklahoma vs. Stewart Waterhouse 1996 (Box 2)
    - Town Zoning Board of Appeals, Township of Perry vs. James P. Dacey (Box 2)
    - Walker vs. Lautner 1995 (Box 2)
    - Wood vs. Detroit Automobile Insurance Exchange 1982 (Box 2)
  - Other Materials
    - The Alanson Armory Gun Store (Box 2)
    - American Council on Economic Security (Box 2)
    - Camp Grayling 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Change in Leadership of Michigan Militia 1998 (Box 2)
    - Charlevoix County Land Dispute 1996 (Box 2)
    - Detroit African American Militia/Detroit Constitutional Militia 1996 (Box 2)
    - Freedom Church 1994-1997 (Box 2)
    - Hand-written Notes (Box 2)
    - Manual, Handbook, and By-laws of Militia (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Montana Freemen, Jordan, Montana (Box 2)
    - News and Press Releases from Militia (Box 2)
    - NRA's relation and stance on Militia Movement 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Northern Michigan Planned Parenthood (Box 2)
    - Republic of Texas Anti-Government Group 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Steven Allen Lynn Investigation 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Third Continental Congress 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Training, Recruitment, and other records related to activities of militia (Box 2)
    - United States Heritage Legion (Box 2)
    - US Department of Treasury, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, and Firearms (Box 2)
    - Village of Pellston Gun Law 1994 (Box 3)
- Collected Resources and Publications 1994-1999
  The Collected Resources and Publications series (2.r linear feet) contains articles, newsletters, clippings, books, and other similar materials collected by Olson, which he used for personal reference. Most are related to his and the militias' views on politics, religion, and other social issues. Many of these resources were exchanged between Olson and those he associated with having shared similar views.
  - Articles and Essays on Militia Movement (Box 3)
  - Bruno, Gary (Licensing Issue) (Box 3)
  - Christianity and Religious Groups (Box 3)
  - Committee on Un-American Activities, House of Representatives 1958-1962 (Box 3)
  - Conspiracies in US and International Politics, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Conspiracies involving Oklahoma City Bombing (Box 3)
  - Conspiracies involving President William Jefferson Clinton (Box 3)
  - Conspiracies involving Waco, Texas (Box 3)
  - Constitutionists Networking Center (Box 3)
  - Contact: The Phoenix Project 1995-1998 (Box 3)
  - Counsel American Individual Rights Enforcement 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Criminal Politics Magazine 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Elections 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - The Federalist 1999 (Box 3)
  - Gulf War Syndrome (Box 3)
  - Gun Control/2nd Amendment, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Gun Owners of America and related organizations (Box 3)
  - Guns (Box 3)
  - Hill, Michael (Ohio Incident) 1995 (Box 4)
  - International Affairs and Treaties (Box 4)
  - Kjos Ministries (Box 4)
  - Land Use and Zoning (Box 4)
  - Legal and Legislative (Box 4)
  - Legal Challenge to Emergency Government (Box 4)
  - The McAlvany Intelligence Advisor 1993-1999 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Electors Association 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Militia Review Newsletter (Box 4)
  - Miller, Clayton (Investigation) 1993 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - National Confederation of Citizen Militias 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - New, Michael (Court-Martial) 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - The New American Newsletter (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Articles and Clippings (Box 4)
  - Other Newsletters, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Other Published Material Related to US and World History, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Patriot Report Newsletter 1994 (Box 4)
  - Political Essays and Speeches 1950-1954, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Posey, Tom and Tom Wiberly Trials 1994 (Box 5)
  - Relevance Newsletter 1994 (Box 5)
  - Resurrection News and Fax Network 1995-1997 (Box 5)
  - Songs and Poetry (Box 5)
  - Trials of Tom Posey and Tom Wiberly 1994 (Box 5)
  - United Nations (Box 5)
  - US Armed Forces (Box 5)
  - Weekly Update 1996 (Box 5)
  - Wiberly, Tom (Box 5)
    (see Posey, Tom)
  - Y2K (Box 5)
  - Books
    - Editors of the Intelligence Review The Ugly Truth about the ADL, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Hoy, Claire and Victor Ostrovsky By War of Deception: A Devastating Insider's Portrait of the Mossad, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Ruhling, Richard G. The Fall of America: A Survivor's Manual, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Townsend, Benjamin The Powers that Be!: The battle rages between Church and State, 1993 (Box 5)